<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!--


<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
-->

<!-- test -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
<!--
<!ENTITY RFC7348 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7348.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7665 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7665.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8300 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8300.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-sfc-hierarchical SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sfc-hierarchical-05.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-netslices-usecases SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-netslices-usecases-02.xml">
-->
<!--
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-qiang-coms-architecture SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-qiang-coms-architecture-00.xml">
-->
<!--
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-qiang-coms-netslicing-information-model SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-qiang-coms-netslicing-information-model-01.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-defoy-coms-subnet-interconnection SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-defoy-coms-subnet-interconnection-01.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-qiang-coms-netslicing-information-model SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-qiang-coms-netslicing-information-model-01.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-mpls SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-mpls-11.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-6man-segment-routing-header SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-6man-segment-routing-header-08.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-nsdt-teas-ns-framework   SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-nsdt-teas-ns-framework-02.xml">
-->
<!--<!ENTITY I-D.draft-homma-rtgwg-slice-gateway SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-homma-rtgwg-slice-gateway-01.xml">-->
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-contreras-teas-slice-nbi SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-contreras-teas-slice-nbi-01.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-teas-sf-aware-topo-model SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-teas-sf-aware-topo-model-05.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-teas-enhanced-vpn SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-teas-enhanced-vpn-05.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-nsdt-teas-ns-framework SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-nsdt-teas-ns-framework-02.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
      please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-nsdt-teas-transport-slice-definition-03">
  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->


<!--test2-->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="draft-nsdt-transport-slice-definition">
    IETF Definition of Transport Slice
    </title>

    <author fullname="Reza Rokui" initials="R." surname="Rokui">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>reza.rokui@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Shunsuke Homma" initials="S." surname="Homma">
      <organization abbrev="NTT">NTT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>
        <email>shunsuke.homma.fp@hco.ntt.co.jp</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <author fullname="Kiran Makhijani" initials="K." surname="Makhijani">
      <organization abbrev="Futurewei">Futurewei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kiranm@futurewei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Luis M. Contreras"
            initials="LM."
            surname="Contreras">
      <organization abbrev="Telefonica">
        Telefonica
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <email>luismiguel.contrerasmurillo@telefonica.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date/>

    <area>rtg</area>

    <workgroup>teas</workgroup>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
		  This document describes the definition of a slice in the transport networks and its characteristics. The purpose
		  here is to bring clarity and a common understanding of the transport slice concept and describe
		  related terms and their meaning. It explains how transport slices can be used in end to end network slices, or independently.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
	<!-- SH-28Jan:  modified the following text for  emphasizing  benefitial features of network slicing. -->
    	<t>
		A number of use cases benefit from establishing a transport connectivity according to the assurance of a specific set of network resources.
       Some such  services which might benefit from the
       transport slices are:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>5G services (e.g. eMBB, URLLC, mMTC)(See <xref target="TS.23.501-3GPP"/>)</t>
          <t>Network wholesale services</t>
          <t>Network infrastructure sharing among the operators</t>
          <t>NFV connectivity (Data Center Interconnect)</t>
          <t>VPNs with specific characteristics</t>
        </list>
       </t>
	   <t>
		   This document defines the concept of transport slices that provide
		   connectivity with specific use of network resources between a number
		   of end points over a shared network infrastructure.
		   Transport slices are created and managed within the scope of
		   transport networks (e.g.  IP, MPLS, optical). They are
		   expected to enable a diverse set of applications that have different
		   requirements on communication to coexist on the same network
		   infrastructure. </t>

	   <t>
		   Transport slices relate to a more general topic of network
		   slicing. It is not the goal of this document to define this broader
		   concept, but in general, it is a methodology to describe the logical
		   partitioning of network resources associated with a service or an
		   application. </t>

    </section>

    <section title="Terms and Abbreviations">
     <t>The terms and abbreviations used in this document are listed below.
       <list style="symbols">
 <!--        <t>E2E network slice: End-to-End network slice</t>  -->
         <t>E2E NS: End to End Network Slice</t>
         <t>TS: Transport Slice</t>
	     <t>TSC: Transport Slice Controller</t>
			 <!-- <t>TNC: Transport Network Controller</t> -->
         <t>EP: Endpoint</t>
         <t>EU: End User</t>
         <t>NBI: NorthBound Interface</t>
         <t>SBI: SouthBound Interface</t>
 <!--        <t>NF: Network Function</t>
         <t>SF: Service Function</t>
         <t>DPI: Deep Packet Inspection</t>
         <t>WAF: Web Application Firewall</t> -->
         <t>SLO: Service Level Objective</t>
         <t>SLA: Service Level Agreement</t>
         <t>MTBF: Mean Time Between Failures</t>
         <t>MTTR: Mean Time To Repair</t>
      </list>
     </t>
    <t>
	Author's notes: This list may be non-exhaustive. Also, a light explanation for each term would be required.  Or this section may be removed if it isn't needed.
    </t>
    </section>




    <section title="Definition and Scope of Transport slice">
		<!--<section title="Transport Slice Definition">
			 -->

        <t>
    The basic definition of a transport slice is as follows:
      </t>
        <t>
"A transport slice is a logical network topology connecting a number of endpoints
and a set of shared or dedicated network resources, which
are used to satisfy  specific Service Level Objectives (SLO)".
</t>


        <t>
	   SLOs are used to describe different network resources associated with the service delivered and corresponding parameters necessary to realize the transport slice.
      </t>
        <t>
			Transport slice should be technology-agnostic, and the means for realization can be chosen
			depending on several factors such as service requirements, specifications or capabilities
			of underlying infrastructure. The structure and different characteristics of transport slices
			are described in the following  sections.
       </t>
      </section>

    <section anchor="TS-Char" title="Transport Slice System Characteristics">

        <t>
			The characteristics here describe the properties and main functionality related to different
			components of a system that supports transport slices.
		</t>

        <section title="Service Level Objectives on Transport Slice">
        <t>
			A transport slice is defined in terms of several quantifiable objectives or SLOs. These objectives define a set of
			network resource parameters or values necessary to provide a service a given transport slice. SLOs need not concern
			with 'how' will they get implemented or realized in the underlying networks. They may be defined along
		   the dimensions of operations (time, capacity, compute...), reliability and, availability attributes. A non-exhaustive
		   list of characteristics types for transport slice is described below:
            <list style="symbols">
			<t>Guaranteed Bandwidth: assurance of minimum or range of the bandwidth requirement. Requested unidirectionally. <!--, however might be dependent on availability of the resource on the return path--></t>
			<t>Guaranteed Latency: maximum permissible network delay when transmitting between source and destination endpoints. Requested unidirectionally.
				The latency is measured  in terms of network characteristics (excluding application-level latency). <xref target="RFC2681" /> and <xref target="RFC7679" /> discuss round trip times and one-way metrics, respectively.
		    </t>
			<t>Minimal permissible jitter: packet delay variation (PDV) as defined by <xref target="RFC3393"/>
                 is measured by the difference in the one-way delay between selected packets
				 in a flow. Minimizing variations in the delay are important for real-time applications, therefore, jitter-prevention
				 parameter provide minimal permissible jitter expectations for a flow.
			 </t>
			<t>Packet loss rate: To specify permissible packet loss rate between two endpoints. For critical networks,
				this number may be very close to zero. See <xref target="RFC7680" />.
			</t>
			<t>NF resources: The endpoints in <xref target="endpvar"/> performance depend on resource allocated to
				those functions and can be specified in terms of compute, memory and access control objectives points. See <xref target="NFVGST" />.
			 </t>
			<t> Availability: concerns with how quickly network becomes available after a fault. The requirements are
				 specified through Meant time between failures (MTBF), and Mean time to repair (MTTR) to acquire availability metrics.
			</t>
			<t>Resource redundancy: represents reliability attributes in which a backup or duplicate resources such as
				 path (same SLOs - latency, bandwidth, etc.), network functions (same compute, memory, etc.)
				 To meet no packet loss objective, packet replication maybe necessary to guarantee that at least packets
				 from one path was achieved. However, we should consider this as 'how' aspect of objective and not 'what'.
			 </t>
			 <t>Security: The objective of securing a transport slice concern with three attributes:
				 a) end-to-end encryption between source and destination endpoints, this can be seen as the logical link between
				 source and destination end points requiring encryption, b) Authentication and access control (ACLs) objectives
				 to permit data on this transport slice, c) Isolation, is also a characteristic of security, to prevent interference
				 between two or more slices or other flows on the same infrastructure. Isolation is implied by the definition of
				 transport slice itself (logical partitioning...).
		     </t>
			 <t>
	Resolution of guarantee: The above objectives can be resolved in to  either
	hard or soft guarantees. A hard guarantee is the one that
	is not affected by other traffic.
	In a soft guarantee, a violation (of the guarantee) may occur in rare
	cases due to resource interference.  In
    such cases, the guarantee will be maintained by the network controller
      within a certain tolerance level of that objective.
	  Note that a hard guarantee does not prevent from hardware failures, such as losing a node.
	  Additional protection against such issues is possible, by specifying those characteristics separately (see item "resource redundancy" below).

      Note also that the hard and soft guarantees do not say anything
      about the specific implementation of how these guarantees are
      achieved. Different implementations might use different
      techniques, from avoiding oversubsription to dedicating
      particular links or their virtual fractions to particular
      transport slices.
  </t>

  <t> Resource isolation: In some cases it may be necessary to dedicate
   specific resources to the slice, for instance, for security reasons.
   </t>
             <t>etc.</t>

            </list>
			The framework <xref target="I-D.nsdt-teas-ns-framework"/> may further specify mechanisms for the
            performance, assurance and monitoring of these objectives.
           </t>
           <t>
			Note: Additional objectives may be necessary to capture, such as specifying
			well defined paths or domains that a slice may transit. A transport slice
			 carries multiple flows between the 2 endpoints, therefore objectives should also
			say if they are aggregates or on per flow basis and in such case to be specific enough for the system to be able to identify these specifics (subset of flows).</t>
		   <t> Further description  of a set of measurable attributes is captured in <xref target="I-D.contreras-teas-slice-nbi"/>.
           </t>
		   <t>
			  SLA vs SLO discussion: In defining transport slices, the term  SLO instead of SLA is used even though SLAs are more commonly
			  used term by the operators. SLOs are definitive and measurable parameters associated with a
			  service, therefore, network resource and connectivity requirements are defined accurately. In contrast,
			   service level agreements represent contracts for a service between a service provider
			   and a service consumer (or subscriber). Providers then translate SLA into SLO; these translations vary from
			   one service provider to the other.
			  Therefore, all through within the scope of transport slices term SLO will be used.
		   </t>

        <section title="Isolation discussion">
	<t>
		Due to overloading of the term, a further discussion is added to highlight two
		aspects of isolation, first the resolution of isolation of an objective (as described above) and second, the dedicated use or a hard-separation perspective of the resource.
	</t>
			<t>
	Providing a hard resolution of guarantee for the characteristics of a
	transport slice means that the behavior and performance of other transport slices
   should not impact that slice, even if they run over the same underlying
   infrastructure or use logically shared network resources.
   </t>
   <t>
	  In the context of soft resolution of guarantees, since the transport slices are
	  logically partitioned over the
      shared resources, a certain degree of commitment to the guarantee
      is expected even when it is not hard.  When the shared resource
      pools begin to become saturated, SLO violations can happen,
      however, impacting only the performance or operation of service
      associated with the transport slice.
   </t>
   <t>
   This degree of isolation can be derived from availability
   characteristics requested, such as whether a hard or soft guarantee was
   requested. Requesting a hard guarantee may commit more resources
   than would be required for a softer limit.</t>
   <t> In addition, resource isolation
	   may be applied to ensure dedicated access to a particular node, for instance. In such
	   requests a dedicated allocation to a link, node and/or other resources to create a
	   transport slice for a particular service. For example, a mission-critical service
	   may ask for a dedicated router and/or a link or port for complete isolation from other
	   services.
   </t>
   <t>
   When realizing a transport slice, a network controller should be
   responsible for allocating and providing resources according to the specified
   objectives.
   </t>
	<t> SLO violations can occur for two reasons and corresponding statements apply
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>
      Shared resource interference: i.e. multiple transport slices
      simultaneously share the same resource, and one of them consume
      the resource in surplus.  If the SLO guarantees are strictly
      required, then the network controller can be informed of this by
      requesting a hard guarantee. Note that the terms hard and soft
      limit are requirement oriented and different from what is
	  specified in, <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-enhanced-vpn"/>). </t>

     <t>
	   Resource failure or fault occurs, such as a link or node failure.
       Where it is important to defend against these, the relevant
       characteristics on resource redundancy (and perhaps some
       other characteristics on restoration speed and other factors) need to be specified.
	     <list style="symbols">
		  <t> Restoration isolation: the network is not impacted for a period
			  longer than the given time. For example,
			  failover or the service restoration takes no longer than
			  some number of seconds. This is specified by Availability  SLO.</t>
		  <t> Protection isolation: the network path is protected with specified backup path.
		    This is specified by Availability  SLO. </t>
          </list>
          </t>
      </list>
	  </t>
	</section>

    </section>
		<!--</section>-->


        <section anchor="endpvar" title="Endpoint Variation">
			<t>
				Transport slice endpoints are the terminating or originating nodes requiring connectivity
				with specific SLO. Endpoints may be devices or functions.
	</t>
        <section title="Types of Endpoints">
			<t>
				There are two types of endpoints based on the functions they perform.
		   <list style="hanging">
			<t hangText="Transport type EP:">
			This type of end point performs forwarding customer payload without any modification. E.g. routers, switches.
			</t>
			<t hangText="Service type EP:">
				This type of endpoint manipulates, processes or modifies the user data payload (based on policies). A
				non-exhaustive list of service functions includes: firewalls, WAN and application acceleration,
				Deep Packet Inspection (DPI), server load balancers, NAT44 <xref target="RFC3022" />, NAT64 <xref target="RFC6146" />, HTTP header
				enrichment functions, and TCP optimizers.  The generic term "L4-L7 services" is often used to
				describe such service functions (SFs).

			</t>
		</list>

	    </t>
		<t>
		This document leverages the term Network Function (NF) to represent both types of endpoints in
		<xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-sf-aware-topo-model"/>.
		</t>
		</section>

        <section title="Connectivity Patterns">
		<t>
		 Endpoints may be connected point to point (P2P), point to multipoint (P2MP), multi-point to point (MP2P), or multi-point to multi-point (MP2MP) based
         on the topology requested by the customer.
		   <list style="hanging">
			<t hangText="P2P pattern: ">
			P2P type of connections are between 2 endpoints like a pseudowire, or a logical link. The interconnections
				must represent the SLOs as requested by the customer.
			</t>
			<t hangText="P2MP/MP2P/MP2MP patterns: ">
				P2MP/MP2P/MP2MP type connections will interconnect two or more endpoints together (one to many,
				many to one, many to many), representing an abstract
				topology or graph. When describing P2MP/MP2P/MP2MP scenarios it should be possible for each logical link to have
				different SLO than the other link in the same graph. <!-- Typical SLO definitions here are point2cloud-->
			</t>
		</list>
	    </t>
       </section>
       </section>


        <section anchor="Vertical-Concept" title="Vertical Transport Slice">
        <t>
			Transport slice may follow a hierarchical relationship that would provide a vertical structure to it. This is used
			for  building multi-layer slices in which each layer provides an abstraction, as well as an independent
			monitoring, performance, control and management of the resources.
			The vertical transport slice characteristic maybe used in 2 forms:
			<list style="symbols">
			  <t> The Transport slice itself where it represents a hierarchy of abstracted transport slices. In this case, realization
				  will be done just once with a particular technology.  Thus, the lowest transport slice in the hierarchy that
				  can not be decomposed further will be one to one mapping to its instance of realized transport slice.</t>
			  <t> Each layer (physical, datalink, or IP) has its own set of resources that  can be provided to the upper layer as
				  a transport slice. Thus, transport slice at one layer is used by the layer above. This type of
				  multi-layer vertical
				 transport slice associates resources at different layers. For example, an IP transport slice
				 would utilize one or more optical transport slice.  In this case, realization
				will be done for  a particular technology at that particular layer. Thus, the lowest transport slice in this type of hierarchy that
				can not be decomposed further will be an instance of realized physical layer transport slice.</t>
			</list>

        </t>

        <figure anchor="fig_HNS" title="Transport Slice Vertical and Horizontal Composition">
          <artwork align="center">
		<![CDATA[
         <======================== TS1 ========================>
         <=====TS11=======>  <==============TS12===============>
                             <====TS121====>  <=====TS122======>
             .--.             .--.                .--.
            (    )--.        (    )--.           (    )--.
            .'         '     .'         '        .'        '
  [EU-x]   (  Network-1  )  (  Network-2  ) ... (  Network-3 )  [EU-y]
            `-----------'    `-----------'       `----------'
         |                |                                   |
         |   Operator-y   |           Operator-z              |

  Legend:
    TSnnn: Level 3 vertical transport slice nnn
    TSnn:  Level 2 vertical transport slice nn
    TSn:   Level 1 transport Slice n
    ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t><xref target="fig_HNS"/> shows the transport slice hierarchy. Slices TS11 and TS12 are composed together to form TS1 that is the top level transport slice definition, TS121 and TS122 collectively define TS12. The SLO for bandwidth guarantee will be shared and latency guarantee will be split into latency in networks 2 and 3. To emphasize the hierarchical structure, consider Network-2 and Network-3 are in the same administrative domain but use different transport technologies SR and L2VPN respectively. Then instead of presenting 2 transport slices, Operator-z can expose only one transport slice TS12 abstracting the underlying transport technology details.
		<list style="empty">
		  <t> Note: The specification to connect TS121 and TS122 are similar to those connecting TS12 and TS11.</t>
		</list>
      </t>

      </section>
      <section title="Horizontal Composition of Transport slice">
	<t> In contrast, horizontal transport slices enable the composition of multiple realized transport slices. Since transport slices
		are not necessarily a single  encapsulation tunnel and may traverse through different data planes, each realized transport slice will require
		a stitching, interworking or mapping function. These stitching functions can be viewed as a type of intermediate network function endpoints.
		For instance in <xref target="fig_HNS"/>, TS11 and TS12 are horizontal transport slices. If we assume that TS11 is an L2 tunnel and TS12 is an SRV6 based path, then a 'Service type EP' (not shown in the figure) is needed for translation.
    </t>
    <t>
	Author's notes: This  service type EP is  a new type of transport slice specific service function. We may call it transport slice
	gateway.
    </t>

    </section>

    </section>
      <section title="Transport Slice Structure">
       <t>
        A transport slice has a set of connections and various endpoints to form a logical network. The goal is to achieve specific SLO for a customer
        as shown in  <xref target="fig_Transport-NS"/>. The endpoints may be user equipment, any physical or virtual network functions (PNF/VNF),
        or any network service for that matter. Similarly,  connections may be virtual or physical links of any type of technology.
       </t>

      <figure anchor="fig_Transport-NS" title="Transport slice">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[


             ____________________________
[EP11]------/                           /--[EP21]
           /                           /
[EP12]----/     Transport Slice       /----[EP22]
  :      /        (SLOs e.g.         /
  :     / B/W > x bps, Delay < y ms)/
[EP1m]-/___________________________/-------[EP2n]

== == == == == == == == == == == == == == == == == ==

           .--.               .--.
[EP11]    (    )- .          (    )- .     [EP21]
         .'         '  SLO  .'         '
[EP12]  (  Network-1 ) ... (  Network-p )  [EP22]
 :       `-----------'      `-----------'     :
[EP1m]                                     [EP2n]

Legend
  SLOs in terms of attributes, e.g. BW, delay.
  EP: Endpoint
  B/W: Bandwidth

  ]]></artwork>
      </figure>


      <t>
      <xref target="fig_Transport-NS"/> illustrates a case where a single transport
      slice provides connectivity between any pair of endpoints with specific characteristics for SLO
      (i.e., assuring bandwidth to at least x bps and transmission delay to be less than y ms).
      The endpoints may be distributed in the underlay networks, and transport slice can be deployed across multiple
      network domains. Also, the endpoints on the same transport slice may belong to the same address space.
      </t>

      <t>
      The "Transport Slices" provides various connections with certain
      SLO between various endpoints whereas the transport slice realization addresses its implementation using various technologies.
      In short, the structure of a transport slice involves both definition and its realization.
      </t>

			<!--
	<t> A "transport slice" addresses a set of technology-agnostic connections between various
		endpoints with certain SLOs.  The managing entity or operating stakeholder of a transport slice is
		called a Transport Slice Controller.
    </t>

   <t>
       Transport slice realization uses specific technologies in the operator's network.
       The realization may require allocating appropriate resources into one or more networks and a mapping to transport slice. The managing entity realizing a transport slice is
		referred to as the network controller. </t>
-->
   <t>
	   A transport slice is built based on a request from a higher operations
	   system.
		The interface to higher operations systems should express the needed
		connectivity in a technology-agnostic way, and slice customers don't need
		to recognize concrete configurations based on the technologies (e.g being
		more declarative than imperative).
		The request to instantiate a transport slice is represented with some
		indicators such as SLO, and technologies are selected and managed
		accordingly.
    </t>
     <t>
	In the context of network slices, the term sub-slice or slice-subnet comes up
	in other standard organizations, however, w.r.t. the IP/MPLS based
	transport networks these terms are all equivalent.
       </t>

	<t>Furthermore, the structure of transport slices may be layered vertically or composed horizontally, i.e. operationally,
			 a transport slice maybe decomposed in two or more transport slices which are then
			independently realized and managed. This is further described in <xref target="Vertical-Concept"/>.</t>

	 	<section anchor="actors" title="Stakeholders">
			<t> A transport slice and its realization involves the following stakeholders and it is relevant
				to define them for consistent terminology.
	   	<list style="hanging">
			<t hangText="Customer or User:">
		A customer is a user of transport slice. Customers may request for
		monitoring of associated resources or specific changes to them. A user
		may either directly manage its service by interfacing  with the
		transport slice controller or indirectly through an orchestrator. </t>
			<t hangText="Orchestrator:">
		An orchestrator is an entity that aggregates different services, resource
		and network requirements. It interfaces with the transport slice controllers.</t>
			<t hangText="Transport Slice Controller (TSC):">
	It realizes a transport slice in the network, maintains and monitors
	the run-time state of resources and topologies associated with it.
				A well-defined interface is needed between different types of transport slice controller and different types of orchestrator.
	A transport slice operator (or slice operator for short) manages one or more transport slices using the Transport Slice Controller(s).
			</t>
			<t hangText="Transport Network Controller:">
        is some form of network infrastructure controller that offers
        network resources to TSC to realize a particular transport
        slice. These may be existing network controllers associated with one
        or more specific technologies that may be adapted to the function of realizing transport slices in a network. </t>
		</list> </t>

		</section>
	 <section anchor="interfaces" title="Transport Slice Controller Interfaces">

	 <t> The interworking and inter-operability among the different
		 stakeholders is  required to  provide common means of
		 provisioning, operating and monitoring the transport slices.
		The following communication interfaces are identified (see <xref target="fig_interfaces"/>).

	   	<list style="hanging">
		 <t hangText="TSC Northbound Interface (NBI):">
       The TSC Northbound Interface is an interface between a higher level system, e.g. 'E2E network
       slice orchestrator' and the 'Transport slice controller'. It is a technology agnostic interface. Over this NBI, slice characteristics and other requirements can be informed to TSC and current state of a transport slice may be requested.
		 </t>
		 <t hangText="TSC Southbound Interface (SBI):">
       The TSC Southbound Interface is an interface between 'Transport
       slice controller' and network controller(s). These interfaces are
       technology-specific and can utilize many of the existing data
       models such as L2SM, L3SM, VPN, etc. TSC may request for network resources or request of their current state for SLO assurance.
		 </t>
     <t> Note on technology -agnostic vs -specific use: These terms are used in
     a transport slice's context. A transport slice from customer level in TSC, is not concerned with the underlying
     network protocol or technology (such as L2VPN, L2VPN, etc.) or corresponding service model (L2SM, L3SM, etc.) representing that protocol. Therefore, for example, both L2VPN, L2SM are technology-specific from a customer of a slice's view. Technology-agnostic simply means representing a transport slice completely as a logical entity.
   </t>
 		</list>
        <figure anchor="fig_interfaces" title="Interface of Transport Slice Controller">
          <artwork align="center">
		<![CDATA[
        +------------------------------------------+
        |                Customer                  |
        +------------------------------------------+
                             A
                             |
                             V
        +------------------------------------------+
        |         A higher level system            |
        |   (e.g e2e network slice orchestrator)   |
        +------------------------------------------+
                             A
                             | TSC NBI
                             V
        +------------------------------------------+
        |         Transport Slice Controller       |
        +------------------------------------------+
                             A
                             | TSC SBI
                             V
        +------------------------------------------+
        |           Network Controller(s)          |
        +------------------------------------------+

    ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        </t>
	  </section>
 <section title="Transport slice Realization">
	 <t>
	 Realization of a Transport Slice is a mapping of underlying infrastructure with its definition. It is technology specific entity that is created and maintained over southbound interfaces. The Network controller(s) export the connectivity and resource mappings to the TSC. The network controller abstracts the details of underlying resources from the TSC.
 </t> <t>
	 The realization may be achieved in the form of either physical or logical connectivity through VPNs, a variety of tunneling technologies such as segment routing, SFC, etc. Accordingly, endpoints may be realized as physical or logical service or network functions.
 </t>

 </section>
  </section>
    <section title="Relationship with End-to-End Network Slicing">
      <t>
        An end-to-end (E2E) network slice is a complete logical network that provides a service in its entirety with a specific
        assurance to the customer. A transport slice concerns with those assurance aspects only within the transport networks.
        Consider <xref target="fig_E2E-NS"/>,
        where a network operator has an E2E network slice that traverses multiple technology-specific networks. Each of these networks might use
        any number of technologies, including but not limited to IP, MPLS, Fiber-Optics (e.g. WDM, DWDM), Passive Optical Networking (PON), Microwave, etc.
      </t>
      <t>
       Each of these networks includes multiple (physical or virtual) nodes and may also provide network functions beyond simply carrying of technology-specific
       protocol data units. The types of nodes used in any of these networks may include:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Packet/frame processing nodes (e.g., Routers, Switches)</t>
        <t>Application servers</t>
        <t>Service Functions(e.g., Firewall, Loadbalancer)</t>
        <t>Radio Access Network (RAN) components</t>
        <t>Mobile Core components</t>
        <t>Microwave transceivers</t>
        <t>Optical repeaters</t>
        <t>etc.</t></list>
      </t>
      <t>
    Each network may support different technologies and an E2E network slice is a combination of these networks. As an example:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Network 1 might contain multiple 5G RAN nodes connected to a few Cell Site Gateways (CSG) routers. </t>
        <t>Network 2 might have one or more layer-3 routers and layer-2 switches which may run on top of an optical network.</t>
        <t>Network 3 might have a number of 5G RAN nodes connected to Passive Optical Network (PON) switches.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <figure anchor="fig_E2E-NS" title="E2E network slice">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

        <======================= E2E NS ======================>
        <-OS1-> <-TS1-> <-TS2-> <-OS2->   ...   <-TSn-> <-OSm->
       |------------------------------------------------------|
       |    .--.             .--.                .--.         |
       |   (    )--.        (    )--.           (    )--.     |
       |   .'         '     .'         '        .'        '   |
[EU-x] |  (  Network-1  )  (  Network-2  ) ... (  Network-p ) |[EU-y]
       |   `-----------'    `-----------'       `----------'  |
       |                                                      |
       |                      Operator-z                      |
       |------------------------------------------------------|
Legend:
  E2E NS: End-to-end network slice
  TSn: Transport Slice n
  OSm: Other Slice m
  EU-x: End User-x
  EU-y: End User-y

  ]]></artwork>
      </figure>


      <t>
      When an operator-z creates a specific E2E network slice, it may create
      one or more of transport slices and other slices (application logic or other system functions).
      </t>

      <t>
     An independent E2E logical network (called E2E network slice) is created for a service (e.g. CCTV, autonomous driving, HD map, etc.) with a specific network SLO requirement
		e.g. a secure connection with an E2E latency less than 5ms, from End User-x (EU-x) to End User-y (EU-y). EU-x maybe a 5G user equipment such as an infotainment unit in a car, CCTV, or a car for autonomous driving, etc. and
    EU-y in 5G is 5G application server, IMS, etc.
      </t>
      <t>
    In <xref target="fig_E2E-NS"/>,  "E2E NS"  is that logical
    network with requested SLO between EU-x to EU-y and   is
    associated with a customer and a specific service type.
      </t>

	  <!--
      <t>
    As a concrete example, a customer "City of NY" would like to connect all its CCTV cameras for the entire city to one or more locations for viewing or collection. To this end, it requests local carrier - 'operator-z' in NY to create a new E2E network slice with a bandwidth no-less-than 10Mbps from each CCTV coverage area. In this case, a single E2E network slice will be created by the operator-z for the customer "City of NY", service type of CCTV and requested bandwidth connecting all the CCTV camera zones to one or more control-centers for the collection of video data.
      </t>
      <t>
    It may also be possible that more than one customer and/or service types are associated with an E2E network slice.

    For instance, an E2E network slice is associated with not only to service type CCTV
    but another service "Public Safety", i.e. NS ID 10 is used for two services for "City of NY".
      </t>
-->
    </section>



    <section title="Security Considerations">
    <t>
    TBD
    </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>
    This memo includes no request to IANA.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgment">
    <t>
    The entire TEAS NS design team and everyone participating in those discussion has contributed to this draft. Particularly, Eric Gray, Xufeng Liu, Jie Dong, Jeff Tantsura, and Jari Arkko for a thorough review among other contributions.
    </t>
    </section>


  </middle>

  <!-- ***** BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
    &I-D.draft-contreras-teas-slice-nbi;
    &I-D.draft-nsdt-teas-ns-framework;
<!-- &I-D.draft-homma-rtgwg-slice-gateway;-->
    &I-D.draft-ietf-teas-sf-aware-topo-model;
    &I-D.draft-ietf-teas-enhanced-vpn;
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2681"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7679"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7680"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3022"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6146"?>
<!--
    <?i-d include="reference.I-D.draft-contreras-teas-slice-nbi"?>
      <?rfc include="refs.RFC3393"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2681"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7679"?>>

      <?i-d include="reference.I-D.netslices-usecases"?>

      <?i-d include="reference.I-D.defoy-coms-subnet-interconnection"?>

      <?i-d include="reference.I-D.qiang-coms-netslicing-information-model"?>>

    &RFC7348;
    &RFC7665;
    &RFC8300;
    &I-D.draft-netslices-usecases;
    &I-D.draft-qiang-coms-netslicing-information-model;
    &I-D.draft-qiang-coms-architecture;
    &I-D.draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-mpls;
    &I-D.draft-ietf-6man-segment-routing-header;
    &I-D.draft-ietf-sfc-hierarchical;
    &I-D.draft-defoy-coms-subnet-interconnection;
-->
 <!--
      <reference anchor='NFV-Architectural-Framework'
       target='http://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_gs/NFV/001_099/002/01.02.01_60/gs_NFV002v010201p.pdf'>
        <front>
        <title>Network Functions Virtualisation (NFV); Architectural Framework</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        Network Functions Virtualisation (NFV) ETSI Industry Specification Group (ISG)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="December" year="2014"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='OSM-White-Paper'
       target='https://osm.etsi.org/images/OSM-Whitepaper-TechContent-ReleaseONE-FINAL.pdf'>
        <front>
        <title>OSM White Paper</title>
        <author>
        <organization>ETSI</organization>
        </author>
        <date month="October" year="2016"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='TS.36.300-3GPP'
       target='http://www.qtc.jp/3GPP/Specs/36300-830.pdf'>
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 36.300</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="December" year="2007"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='Slicing_Tutrial'
       target='http://netsoft2018.ieee-netsoft.org/program/tutorials/; http://discovery.ucl.ac.uk/10051374/'>
        <front>
        <title>Network Slicing Landscape- Tutorial</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        IEEE NetSoft2018
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="June" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='NECOS'
       target='hhttp://www.h2020-necos.eu'>
        <front>
        <title>Novel Enablers for Cloud Slicing</title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        NECOS
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date/>
        </front>
      </reference>
-->
      <reference anchor='TS.23.501-3GPP'  target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp//Specs/archive/23_series/23.501/23501-g20.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 23.501 (V16.2.0): System Architecture for the 5G System (5GS); Stage 2 (Release 16)
        </title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="September" year="2019"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

	  <reference anchor="RFC3393" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3393">
      <front>
      <title>
      IP Packet Delay Variation Metric for IP Performance Metrics (IPPM)
      </title>
      <author initials="C." surname="Demichelis" fullname="C. Demichelis">
      <organization/>
      </author>
      <author initials="P." surname="Chimento" fullname="P. Chimento">
      <organization/>
      </author>
      <date year="2002" month="November"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3393"/>
      <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC3393"/>
      </reference>

	  <reference anchor='NFVGST' target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_gs/NFV-TST/001_099/008/02.04.01_60/gs_nfv-tst008v020401p.pdf">
        <front>
		<title>
			NFVI Compute and Network Metrics Specification
		</title>
        <author>
        <organization> ETSI </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="Febuary" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
