<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!--


<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" []>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
-->

<!-- test -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->
<!--<!ENTITY RFC5921 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5921.xml">-->
<!--
<!ENTITY RFC7348 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7348.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7665 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7665.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8300 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8300.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-sfc-hierarchical SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-sfc-hierarchical-05.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-netslices-usecases SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-netslices-usecases-02.xml">
-->
<!--
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-qiang-coms-architecture SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-qiang-coms-architecture-00.xml">
-->
<!--
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-qiang-coms-netslicing-information-model SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-qiang-coms-netslicing-information-model-01.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-defoy-coms-subnet-interconnection SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-defoy-coms-subnet-interconnection-01.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-qiang-coms-netslicing-information-model SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-qiang-coms-netslicing-information-model-01.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-mpls SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-spring-segment-routing-mpls-11.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-6man-segment-routing-header SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-6man-segment-routing-header-08.xml">

-->
<!--<!ENTITY I-D.draft-homma-rtgwg-slice-gateway SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-homma-rtgwg-slice-gateway-01.xml">-->
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-contreras-teas-slice-nbi SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-contreras-teas-slice-nbi-01.xml">
<!--
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-teas-sf-aware-topo-model SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-teas-sf-aware-topo-model-05.xml">
-->
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-teas-enhanced-vpn SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-teas-enhanced-vpn-05.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-nsdt-teas-ns-framework SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-nsdt-teas-ns-framework-02.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-ietf-teas-yang-te-topo SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-ietf-teas-yang-te-topo-22.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.draft-nsdt-teas-ns-framework SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-nsdt-teas-ns-framework-02.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
      please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-nsdt-teas-ietf-network-slice-definition-05">
  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="draft-nsdt-ietf-network-slice-definition">
    Definition of IETF Network Slices 
    </title>

    <author fullname="Reza Rokui" initials="R." surname="Rokui">
      <organization>Nokia</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country>Canada</country>
        </postal>
        <email>reza.rokui@nokia.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Shunsuke Homma" initials="S." surname="Homma">
      <organization abbrev="NTT">NTT</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <region/>
          <code/>
          <country>Japan</country>
        </postal>
        <email>shunsuke.homma.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <author fullname="Kiran Makhijani" initials="K." surname="Makhijani">
      <organization abbrev="Futurewei">Futurewei</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>kiranm@futurewei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Luis M. Contreras"
            initials="LM."
            surname="Contreras">
      <organization abbrev="Telefonica">
        Telefonica
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <country>Spain</country>
        </postal>
        <email>luismiguel.contrerasmurillo@telefonica.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jeff Tantsura"
            initials="J."
            surname="Tantsura">
      <organization abbrev="Apstra, Inc.">
        Apstra, Inc.
      </organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city/>
          <country/>
        </postal>
        <email>jefftant.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>


    <date/>

    <area>rtg</area>

    <workgroup>teas</workgroup>

    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
   This document provides a definition of the term "IETF Network Slice" for
   use within the IETF and specifically within other IETF documents that
   describe or use aspects of network slices.
</t>
<t>
   The document also describes the characteristics of an IETF-network slice,
   describes related terms and their meanings, and explains how
   these IETF network slices can be used in combination with end to end network
   slices or independent of them.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
    	<t>
		A number of use cases benefit from network connections that provide assurance of a specific set of 
        network resources. In this document, as detailed in the subsequent sections, we refer to this connectivity and resource commitment 
        as the IETF-network slice. Services that might benefit from the network slices include but not limited to:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>5G services (e.g. eMBB, URLLC, mMTC)(See <xref target="TS.23.501-3GPP"/>)</t>
          <t>Network wholesale services</t>
          <t>Network infrastructure sharing among operators</t>
          <t>NFV connectivity and Data Center Interconnect</t>
        </list>
       </t>

<t> Editor's Note: TODO  provide forward reference to use case section
</t>

<t>
    Since this assertion is unsubstantiated and expressed as a speculation
it reads like marketing! I suspect we don't need it or the list of
bullets, but maybe you could insert forward references to the sections
that describe the use cases and how a transport slice might be
beneficial in those cases (those would be sections yet to be written).
If, as you seem to imply, the reason for this document is to describe
a term for a concept that has value in certain deployments, I think it
is incumbent on you to describe those cases.
</t>
<t>
This document defines the concept of IETF network slices that provide connectivity with a specific commitment of network resources 
          between a number of end points over a shared network infrastructure. Since the term network slice is quite generic and cannot be described universally, the qualifying term 'IETF' is used to limit the scope of network slice with in the network technologies described and standardized by IETF. 
</t>

	<section title="Rationale">
     <t> 
     IETF network slices are created and managed within the scope of one or more underlying network technologies (e.g., IP, MPLS, optical). 
     They are expected to enable a diverse set of applications that have different requirements to coexist on the same network infrastructure. 
     </t>

	<t>
 IETF network slice is a well-defined structure of connectivity requirements and network resources associated with it. IETF Network slices are defined such that they are independent of 
   the underlying infrastructure connectivity. This allows customer to describe its network resource requirements in a common format, independent of any underlying technologies. The types of underlying networking technologies can be based on any combination of IP, Ethernet, MPLS, and optical technologies.  IETF Network slices also include specification of resources 
   related to network functions required by customer applications.  
    </t>
     <t> 
        <!-- Jeff's comment June16 (coherency/grammar) the para below doesn't read well, please rephrase it. 
        Are we tryig to say that VPN's are primarily focused on segmentaion while slices on assurance (+ segmentation)? Please do let me know and I will rewrite it accoridingly -->
        Traditionally, VPNs have focussed on segmentation, i.e., creation and management of the private networks. They are bound to a specific traffic type and are technology specific. In contrast, IETF network slices concern with the assurance of resources required from the network  and provide a common user interface for describing those resources. A service provider can use many aspects of the VPNs to build the IETF network slices over IETF technologies. 
     </t>

    <t>
	IETF network slices relate to a more general topic of end-to-end network slicing. It is not the goal of this document to define this broader concept, 
    but in general, it is to identify the methodology to describe the logical (or abstract) partitioning of network resources with in the IETF scope associated with a service or an application. 
    </t>
<t> TODO: add normative reference to other document in ITU and 3GPP in framework </t>
    </section>

    </section>

    <section title="Terms and Abbreviations">
     <t>The terms and abbreviations used in this document are listed below.
       <list style="symbols">
         <t>E2E NS: End to End Network Slice</t>
         <t>NS: IETF Network Slice</t>
	     <t>NSC: IETF Network Slice Controller</t>
         <t>EP: Endpoint</t>
         <t>EU: End User</t>
         <t>NBI: NorthBound Interface</t>
         <t>SBI: SouthBound Interface</t>
         <t>SLI: Service Level Indicator
            A well defined quantitative measure of some aspect of the level of service that is provided.</t>
         <t>SLO: Service Level Objective
            A target value or range of values for a service level that is measured by an SLI. 
            A natural structure for SLOs is thus SLI  &lt;= target, or lower bound  &lt;= SLI  &lt;= upper bound.</t>
         <t>SLA: Service Level Agreement
            An explicit or implicit contract with the user of IETF network slice that includes consequences of meeting (or missing) the SLOs they contain.</t>

      </list>
     </t>
<t> Editor's Note: TODO add detailed description in later section on SLO/SLI/SLA. we can 
    move definition from here and to better explain the concept </t>
    <t>
      The above terminology is described in greater detail in the remainder of this document.
    </t>
    </section>




 <section title="Definition and Scope of IETF Network Slice">

 <t>
 The definition of a network slice in IETF context is as follows:

 <!--Jeff's review June16: we already have bunch of definitons in the above section, should we move them here? -->
</t>
<t>
 "An IETF network slice is a logical network topology connecting a number of endpoints with a set of shared or dedicated network resources,
 that are used to satisfy specific Service Level Objectives (SLOs)".
</t>

<t> The text below describes IETF network slices in more details.
</t>
<t>
<!--Jeff's review June16: we are rephrasing defintions already made above -->
   <!-- kiran: A transport slice consists of a set of connections between multiple
   endpoints with a specified connectivity type and one or more SLOs associated with it.
SLOs are used to describe different characteristics of network resources associated with the service delivered and corresponding parameters necessary to 
realize the transport slice.-->
      </t>
 <t>
	IETF Network slice specification is technology-agnostic, and the means for IETF network slice realization can be chosen depending on 
    several factors such as: service requirements, specifications or capabilities of underlying infrastructure. The structure and different 
    characteristics of IETF network slices are described in the following  sections.
 </t>
<t>
<!--
   The term "transport" in transport slice is derived from the definition of Transport Network in the section 1.3.1 of <xref target="RFC5921"/> : 
   A Transport Network provides transparent transmission of user traffic between attached client devices by establishing and maintaining 
   point-to-point or point-to-multipoint connections between such devices. 
-->

  Term "Slice" refers to a set of characteristics that separate one type of 
   user-traffic from other types. 
   IETF Network slice assumes that an underlying network is capable of changing 
   the configurations of the network devices on demand, through in-band signaling or via controller(s) and fulfilling all or some of 
   SLOs to all of the traffic in the slice or to specific flows.
       </t>
  
      </section>

    <section anchor="TS-Char" title="IETF Network Slice System Characteristics">

      <t>
			The following subsections describe the characteristics of IETF network slices.
		</t>

        <section title="Service Level Objectives for IETF Network Slices">
        <t>
			An IETF network slice is defined in terms of several quantifiable characteristics or service level objectives (SLOs). These objectives define a set of
			network resource parameters or values necessary to provide a service as requested for a given IETF network slice. SLOs do not describe
			'how' the IETF network slices will be implemented or realized in the underlying network layers.  Instead, they are defined in terms of dimensions of operations (time, capacity, etc.), availability and other attributes.
      An IETF network slice can have one or more SLOs associated with it, all SLO's combined to form an SLA. 
      The SLO values are defined unidirectionally and for specific subsets of two or more endpoints (i.e. for a subset of connections in IETF network slice).
    </t>
    <t>      
      The SLOs and values associated with them that are exposed to the user of an IETF network slice, are in the form of Service Level Indicators (SLIs). If for example the range of latencies a network can provide is 50ms-100ms, then this would be the range of values the IETF network slice user should be able to request, it would be as low as 50ms or as high as 100ms or anything in between.
      The values of requested SLOs should always be in the range of values supported. The underlying networks must provide means to monitor and measure the performance of network 
    slices against the SLOs requested and verify that they are being met. Some SLOs can be measured directly through a collection of metrics and statistics from the network (commonly known as 'telemetry'), while others are deduced from measurable objectives and may require additional tools or mechanisms to measure their target values. 
    </t>

    <section anchor="minSLO" title="Minimal Set of SLOs">
    <t>
      This document defines a minimal set of SLOs and later systems or standards could extend this set and define more SLOs. For example, we included Guaranteed bandwidth which is the minimum requested bandwidth for the IETF network slice. The later standard might define other SLOs related to bandwidth if needed.
    </t>
<!-- WRT SLIs take a look at: https://landing.google.com/sre/sre-book/chapters/service-level-objectives/#indicators-o8seIAcZ - it has become the industry standard-->
    <t>
      Accordingly, SLOs can be categorized in to 'Directly Measurable Objectives' or 'Indirectly Measurable Objectives' as follows:
    </t>    

    <t>      
      Some of the 'Directly Measurable Objectives' are:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Guaranteed Minimum Bandwidth</t>
        <t>Guaranteed Maximum Latency</t>
        <t>Maximum permissible delay variation</t>    
		    <t>Maximum permissible packet loss rate</t>
        <t>Availability</t>
        <t>Other objectives could be specified</t>
      </list>

      Some of the 'Indirectly Measurable Objectives' are: 
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Security</t>
        <t>others objectives such as geographical restrictions, maximum occupancy level, etc. could be specified</t>
      </list>

      The definition of these objectives are as follows:

      <list style="symbols">

        <t>Guaranteed Minimum Bandwidth: Minimum guaranteed bandwidth between two endpoints at any time. The bandwidth is measured in data rate 
        units of bits per second and is measured unidirectionally.</t>

        <t>Guaranteed Maximum Latency: Upper bound of network latency when transmitting between two endpoints. The latency is 
        measured  in terms of network characteristics (excluding application-level latency). <xref target="RFC2681" /> and <xref target="RFC7679" /> 
        discuss round trip times and one-way metrics, respectively.</t>

        <t>Maximum permissible delay variation: Packet delay variation (PDV) as defined by <xref target="RFC3393"/>, is measured by 
        the difference in the one-way delay between sequential packets in a flow. Minimizing variations in the delay is important for real-time 
        applications.</t>

        <t>Maximum permissible packet loss rate: is defined by
          the ratio of packets dropped to packets transmitted between two endpoints. See <xref target="RFC7680" /></t>

        <t> Availability: is defined as the ratio of uptime to total_time(uptime+downtime), where uptime is the time the IETF network slice is available
         in accordance with the SLOs associated with it.</t>


	<t>Security: This objective may request for encryption <xref target="RFC4303"/> between two end-points explicitly to meet architecture recommendations as in <xref target="TS33.210"/> or for compliance with <xref target="HIPAA"/> <xref target="PCI"/>. Other security requests may be made as specified in [draft-ietf-i2nsf-capability].
      <list>
	<t> Note: Security violations are not directly observable and cannot be measured as quantifiable metrics. Still, the customer of the IETF network slice should be able to request certain criteria for compliance and identify exceptions and unexpected traffic. For this purpose [i2nsf-nsf-monitoring-data-model] can be leveraged. </t> 
    </list>
</t>
    </list>

      </t>
      
</section> 
 <section anchor="otherSLO" title="Other Objectives">
      <t> 
      Additional objectives, such as certain geographical restrictions or well defined domains that a slice may transit may be necessary. 
    </t>
      <t> 
  <!--Jeff's review - these characteristics are not requested by a client but provided by a client for cases when transport slice is "traffic aware", same goes for "occupancy" EVPN would care about number of MAC addresses while optical transport would not, let's phrase this para differently --> <!--  kiran: added traffice aware-->
      Optionally, when the customer is traffic aware, other traffic specific characteristics may be provided. These include for example,  MTU, traffic-type (e.g., IPv4, IPv6, Ethernet or
      unstructured), or a higher-level behavior to process traffic according to user-application (which may be realized using network functions). </t>
<t> Maximal occupancy for an IETF network slice should be provided. Since it carries traffic for multiple flows between the two endpoints, the objectives should also say if they are for 
      the entire connection, group of flows or on per flow basis. Maximal occupancy should specify the scale of the 
      flows (i.e. maximum number of accommodatable flows) and optionally a maximum number of countable resource  units, e.g IP or MAC addresses a slice might consume.
      </t>
		  
<t>
 With these objectives incorporated, a customer sees IETF network slice as a  dedicated network for its exclusive use. Achieving this may require explicit request for different types of isolation in provider networks as described in 
 <xref target="isolation" />.
</t>
      <t> Additional description of slice attributes is covered in a broader context of 'Generic Network Slice Template' in <xref target="I-D.contreras-teas-slice-nbi"/>. </t>

</section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="tse" title="IETF Network Slice Endpoints">
      <t>The IETF network slice endpoints are the conceptual entities that perform any required conversion, or adaptation, and forwarding of the user traffic. The characteristics of the IETF network slice endpoints (NSE) are:
        <list style="symbols">
          <t> They are conceptual points of connection of a network function, device or application to the IETF network slice</t>
          <t> They are identified in a request provided by the customer of IETF network slice (i.e.  higher level operation systems) during the creation of the IETF network slice</t>
          <t> They are associated with a device,  application and/or network function nodes. A non-exhaustive list of such nodes are routers, switches, firewalls, WAN, 4G/5G RAN nodes, 4G/5G Core nodes, application acceleration, Deep Packet Inspection (DPI), server load balancers, NAT44 <xref target="RFC3022"/>, NAT64 <xref target="RFC6146"/>, HTTP header enrichment functions, and TCP optimizers</t>
          <t> A NSE is identified by its associated node (its IP address, name , ID, etc.), a unique identifier and/or a unique name and other data. A non-exhaustive list of other data includes IP address (v4 or v6), VLAN, port, connectivity type (P2P, P2MP, MP2MP). TBD for more</t>
        </list>
       </t>
       
       <t> Note that the NSE is different from access points (AP) defined in <xref target="RFC8453"/> as an AP is a logical identifier to identify the shared link between the customer and the operator where as NSE is an identifier of an endpoint. Also NSE is different from TE Link Termination Point (LTP) defined in  <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-yang-te-topo"/> as it is a conceptual point of connection of a TE node to one of the TE links on a TE node.</t>
       <t> The NSE is similar to the Termination Point (TP) defined in <xref target="RFC8345"/> and can contain more attributes. NSE could be modeled by augmenting the TP model.</t>
<!--
       <t>Note that TSE concept is similar to the Link Termination Point (LTP) defined in  <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-yang-te-topo"/> and access points (AP) defined in [RFC8453] with an important difference. The main difference between them is that both LTP and AP are about a specific set of implementations based on characterestics of the TE network while NSE is an effort to hide the details of the underlying realizaion. </t>

       <t>AP is a common identifier for the TE link (See section 2.1 RFC8453) and LTP is a conceptual point of connection of a TE node to one of the TE links, terminated by the TE node (see section 3.5  <xref target="I-D.ietf-teas-yang-te-topo"/>) whereas NSE is the connectino point to the transports slice. Note that it might be that the trasport slice is realized in a non-TE network and NSE might not be assocaiate to TE network. The TE characteristic of the network might be taken into consideration during the realization of a transport slice in a TE network.</t>
-->
       <t>There is another type of the endpoints called "IETF Network Slice Realization endpoints (NSREs)". These endpoints are allocated and assigned by the network controller during the realization of an IETF network slice and are technology-specific, i.e. they depend on the network technology used during the IETF network slice realization. They are identified by a node and some associated data. A non-exhaustive list of nodes containing NSREs are routers, switches, PON nodes, Wireless nodes and Optical devices.</t>


       <t> <xref target="fig_tse_tsre"/> shows an example of an IETF network slice and its realization between multiple NSEs and NSREs.</t>

       <figure anchor="fig_tse_tsre" title="An IETF network slice between NSEs and its realization between NSREs">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

  
                         (-------------------)
                        ( IETF-scoped Network )
      DAN1             (                       )                DAN2
   --------  NSRE1 --------                  -------- NSRE2   --------
   |    o |-------o|  A   |                  |  B   |o--------| o    |
   |  NSE1|        --------                  --------         | NSE2 |
   --------        |   (                        )    |        -------- 
        |          |    (                      )     |          |
        |          |     (-------------------)       |          |
        |          |                                 |          |
        |          | <=============================> |          |
        |             IETF Network slice realization            | 
        |                 between NSRE1 and NSRE2               |
        |                                                       |
        | <===================================================> |
             IETF Network slice between NSE1 and NSE2 with SLO1
 
 Legend:
    DAN: Device, application and/or network function
      ]]></artwork>
     </figure>

     <section title="IETF Network Slice Connectivity Types">
       <t> The IETF network slice connection types can be point to point (P2P), point to multipoint (P2MP), multi-point to point (MP2P), or multi-point to  multi-point (MP2MP). They will requested by the higher level operation system. </t>
     </section> 

    </section>

        <section anchor="Vertical-Concept" title="Vertical Composition of IETF Network Slice">
        <t>
			IETF Network slice may follow a hierarchical relationship to provide a vertical structure to it. This is used
			for composing multi-layer slices in which each layer provides an abstraction, as well as an independent
			monitoring, performance, control and management of the resources.
			The vertical IETF Network slice characteristic could be used in 2 forms:
			<list style="symbols">
			  <t> The IETF Network slice itself where it represents a hierarchy of abstracted IETF network slices. In this case, the realization
				  will be done just once with a particular technology.  Thus, the lowest IETF network slice in the hierarchy that
				  can not be decomposed further will be one to one mapping to its instance of the realized IETF network slice.</t>
			  <t> Each layer (physical, datalink, or IP) has its own set of resources that  can be provided to the upper layer as
				  an IETF network slice. Thus, IETF network slice at one layer is used by the layer above. This type of
				  multi-layer vertical IETF network slice associates resources at different layers. For example, an IP IETF network slice
				 would utilize one or more optical IETF network slice.  In this case, the realization
				will be done for  a particular technology at that particular layer. Thus, the lowest IETF network slice in this type of hierarchy that
				can not be decomposed further will be an instance of realized physical layer IETF network slice.</t>
			</list>

        </t>

        <figure anchor="fig_HNS" title="IETF Network Slice Vertical and Horizontal Composition">
          <artwork align="center">
		<![CDATA[
         <======================== NS1 ========================>
         <=====NS11=======>  <==============NS12===============>
                             <====NS121====>  <=====NS122======>
             .--.             .--.                .--.
            (    )--.        (    )--.           (    )--.
            .'         '     .'         '        .'        '
  [EU-x]   (  Network-1  )  (  Network-2  ) ... (  Network-3 )  [EU-y]
            `-----------'    `-----------'       `----------'
         |                |                                   |
         |   Operator-y   |           Operator-z              |

  Legend:
    NSnnn: Level 3 vertical IETF network slice nnn
    NSnn:  Level 2 vertical IETF network slice nn
    NSn:   Level 1 IETF network slice n
    ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
        <xref target="fig_HNS"/> shows the netowrk slice hierarchy. Slices TS11 and TS12 are composed together to form TS1 that is the top 
        level netowrk slice definition, TS121 and TS122 collectively define TS12. The SLO for bandwidth guarantee will be shared and latency 
        guarantee will be split into latency in networks 2 and 3. To emphasize the hierarchical structure, consider Network-2 and Network-3 are 
        in the same administrative domain but use different netowrk technologies respectively. Then instead of presenting 2 
        netowrk slices, Operator-z can expose only one netowrk slice TS12 abstracting the underlying netowrk technology details.
		<list style="empty">
		  <t> Note: The specification to connect TS121 and TS122 are similar to those connecting TS12 and TS11.</t>
		</list>
      </t>

      </section>
      
      <section title="Horizontal Composition of IETF Network Slice">
	<t> In contrast, horizontal IETF network slices enable the composition of multiple realized netowrk slices. Since IETF network slices
		are not necessarily a single  encapsulation tunnel and may traverse through different data planes, each realized IETF network slice will require
		a stitching, interworking or mapping function. These stitching functions can be viewed as a type of intermediate network function endpoints.
		For instance in <xref target="fig_HNS"/>, TS11 and TS12 are horizontal IETF network slices. If we assume that TS11 is an L2 tunnel and TS12 is an SRV6 based path, then a 'Service type EP' (not shown in the figure) is needed for translation.
    </t>
    <t>
	Author's notes: This  service type EP is a new type of IETF network slice specific service function. We may call it IETF network slice
	gateway.
    </t>

    </section>

    </section>
      <section title="IETF Network Slice Structure">

       <t>
        An IETF network slice is a set of connections among various endpoints to form a logical network that meets the SLOs agreed upon.
        <!-- Jeff's comments - the goal is to provide a transport slice that meets the SLO's agreed upon--> <!--kiran: cpmmented
        The goal is to provide connectivity that meets the SLOs agreed upon
        as shown in --> <!-- <xref target="fig_Transport-NS"/>. The endpoints may be user equipment, any physical or virtual network functions (PNF/VNF),
        or any network service for that matter. Similarly,  the connections may be virtual or physical links of any type of technology. -->
         <!-- Jeff's comments - we have already defined what endpoints are, why are we keeping on chewing the definitions?--> <!--kiran: commented-->
       </t>

      <figure anchor="fig_Transport-NS" title="IETF Network slice">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[


             ____________________________
[EP11]------/                           /--[EP21]
           /                           /
[EP12]----/   IETF Network  Slice     /----[EP22]
  :      /        (SLOs e.g.         /
  :     / B/W > x bps, Delay < y ms)/
[EP1m]-/___________________________/-------[EP2n]

== == == == == == == == == == == == == == == == == ==

           .--.               .--.
[EP11]    (    )- .          (    )- .     [EP21]
         .'         '  SLO  .'         '
[EP12]  (  Network-1 ) ... (  Network-p )  [EP22]
 :       `-----------'      `-----------'     :
[EP1m]                                     [EP2n]

Legend
  SLOs in terms of attributes, e.g. BW, delay.
  EP: Endpoint
  B/W: Bandwidth

  ]]></artwork>
      </figure>


      <t>
      <xref target="fig_Transport-NS"/> illustrates a case where an IETF network slice provides connectivity between a set of endpoints pairs 
      with specific characteristics for each SLO (e.g. guaranteed minimum bandwidth of x bps and guaranteed delay of less than y ms). The endpoints 
      may be distributed in the underlay networks, and an IETF network slice can be deployed across multiple network domains. Also, the endpoints 
      on the same IETF network slice may belong to the same address space.
      </t>

      <t>
      <!-- Jeff's comments - can't parse it, please rephrase it-->
      IETF Network slices involve both customer's and provider's views. 
      A customer 'describes' its requirements in terms of connectivity  with specific SLOs.
      Provider networks address those requirements through 'IETF network slice realization' (its implementation) using provider network specific technologies.


      <!--The "Transport Slices" provides various connections with various SLOs between various endpoints whereas the transport slice realization 
      addresses its implementation using various technologies.
      In short, the transport slice involves both its definition and its realization; the transport slice definiton addresses the set of connectivities 
      with required SLOs whereas the transport slice realization addresses how this transport slice is deployed in the network for certain network 
      technologies. -->
      </t>

      <!-- Jeff's comments - "higher" reads really wierd, the direction is South->North (not low->high), let's use the directions accoringly?-->
      <!--
      <t> A transport slice is built based on a request from a higher level operation system. The interface to higher operations systems 
      should express the needed connectivity in a technology-agnostic way, and slice customers don't need to recognize concrete 
      configurations based on the technologies (e.g. being more declarative than imperative). The request to instantiate a transport slice is 
      represented with some indicators such as SLO, and technologies are selected and managed accordingly. 
      </t> -->
      <t> An IETF network slice is requested from an entity (such as an orchestrator or a system-wide controller) performing broader service or application specific functions. 

      The interface from such an entity should express the needed connectivity in a technology-agnostic way and  donot need to recognize configurations based on the technologies (e.g. being more declarative than imperative). 
      The request to instantiate an IETF network slice is 
      only represented with some indicators such as SLOs based on which the underlying technologies are selected and managed. 
      </t>

      <t>
	<!--Entities above the TSC may be managing a broader construct called network slices. --> Often, in other SDOs the term sub-slice or slice-subnet comes up. Some of those are mapped to transport network requirements in the form of an IETF network slice.

  With in the scope of IETF network slices as described in this document, (w.r.t. the IP/MPLS based
	transport networks) there are no definitions for 'sub-slice' or 'slice subnets'. 'IETF network slice' term universally represents SLO and connectivity requirements from those refered to as transport networks in other SDOs.
  <!-- Jeff's comments - equvalent to what? -->
       </t>

	<t>Furthermore, the structure of IETF network slices may be layered vertically or composed horizontally, i.e. operationally,
			 an IETF network slice maybe decomposed in two or more IETF network slices which are then
			independently realized and managed. This is further described in <xref target="Vertical-Concept"/>.</t>
      <!-- Jeff's comments - we have already explained the concept, why are we repeating it again? -->

	 	<section anchor="actors" title="Stakeholders">
			<t> An IETF network slice and its realization involves the following stakeholders and it is relevant
				to define them for consistent terminology.
	   	<list style="hanging">
			<t hangText="Customer or User:">
		A customer is a requester of an IETF  network slice. Customers may request
		monitoring of associated resources or specific changes. A customer
		may either directly manage its service by interfacing with the
		IETF network slice controller or indirectly through an orchestrator. </t>
			<t hangText="Orchestrator:">
		An orchestrator is an entity that composes different services, resource
		and network requirements. It interfaces with the IETF network slice controllers.</t>
			<t hangText="IETF Network Slice Controller (NSC):">
	It realizes an IETF network slice in the underlying network, maintains and monitors
	the run-time state of resources and topologies associated with it.
				A well-defined interface is needed between different types of IETF network slice controllers and different types of orchestrators.
	An IETF network slice operator (or slice operator for short) manages one or more IETF network slices using the IETF Network Slice Controller(s).
			</t>
			<t hangText="Network Controller:">
        is a form of network infrastructure controller that offers
        network resources to NSC to realize a particular network
        slice. These may be existing network controllers associated with one
        or more specific technologies that may be adapted to the function of realizing IETF network slices in a network. </t>
		</list> </t>

		</section>
	 <section anchor="interfaces" title="IETF Network Slice Controller Interfaces">

	 <t> The interworking and interoperability among the different
		 stakeholders to provide common means of
		 provisioning, operating and monitoring the IETF network slices is a mandatory requirement.
		The following communication interfaces are identified (see <xref target="fig_interfaces"/>).

	   	<list style="hanging">
		 <t hangText="TSC Northbound Interface (NBI):">
       The TSC Northbound Interface is an interface between a higher level operation system, e.g. 'E2E network
       slice orchestrator' and the 'E2E network slice controller'. It is a technology agnostic interface. Over this NBI, IETF network slice characteristics and 
       other requirements can be communicated to TSC and the operational state of an IETF network slice may be requested.
		 </t>
		 <t hangText="TSC Southbound Interface (SBI):">
       The TSC Southbound Interface is an interface between 'network 
      slice controller (TSC)'  and network  controller(s). These 
      interfaces are technology-specific and utilize many of the 
      network models.
		 </t>
		
    <!-- Jeff's comments - why are we using: can/should/would here? this is the document that defines what things do, not what they can or should do -kiran: removed can-->

 		</list>
        <figure anchor="fig_interfaces" title="Interface of IETF Network Slice Controller">
          <artwork align="center">
		<![CDATA[
        +------------------------------------------+
        |                Customer                  |
        +------------------------------------------+
                             A
                             |
                             V
        +------------------------------------------+
        |     A higher level operation system      |
        |   (e.g E2E network slice orchestrator)   |
        +------------------------------------------+
                             A
                             | TSC NBI
                             V
        +------------------------------------------+
        |    IETF Network Slice Controller (NSC)   |
        +------------------------------------------+
                             A
                             | TSC SBI
                             V
        +------------------------------------------+
        |           Network Controller(s)          |
        +------------------------------------------+

    ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        </t>
	  </section>
 <section title="IETF Network Slice Realization">
	 <t>
	 Realization of an IETF Network Slice is a mapping of underlying infrastructure with its definition. It is a technology specific 
     entity that is created and maintained over its southbound interfaces. The Network controller(s) export the connectivity and 
     resource mappings to the TSC. The network controller abstracts the details of underlying resources from the TSC.
 </t> 
 
 <t>
	 The realization can be achieved in the form of either physical or logical connectivity through VPNs, a variety of tunneling 
     technologies such as Segment Routing, SFC, etc. Accordingly, endpoints may be realized as physical or logical service or network functions.
 </t>

 </section>
  </section>
    <section anchor="isolation" title="Isolation in IETF Network Slices">
       <section title="Traffic Isolation">
<t>
		This section will describe the scope and use of term isolation.
</t>
       </section>
       <section title="Dedicated Resources">
<t>
		This section explains the scope and use of term dedicated resource in the context of IETF network slices.
</t>
       </section>
  </section>
    <section title="Relationship with End-to-End Network Slice">
      <t>
        An E2E network slice is a complete logical network that provides a service in its entirety with a specific
        assurance to the customer. An IETF network slice concerns with automation and assurance aspects only within the scope of IETF networks and is refered to as transport slice below, as described by other SDOs in the broader context of E2E network slice.
        Consider <xref target="fig_E2E-NS"/>,
        where a network operator has an E2E network slice that traverses multiple technology-specific networks. Each of these networks might use
        any number of technologies, including but not limited to IP, MPLS, Fiber-Optics (e.g. WDM, DWDM), Passive Optical Networking (PON), Microwave, etc.
      </t>
      <t>
       Each of these networks includes multiple (physical or virtual) nodes and may also provide network functions beyond simply carrying of technology-specific
       protocol data units. The types of nodes used in any of these networks may include:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Packet/frame processing nodes (e.g., Routers, Switches)</t>
        <t>Application servers</t>
        <t>Service Functions(e.g., Firewall, Loadbalancer)</t>
        <t>Radio Access Network (RAN) components</t>
        <t>Mobile Core components</t>
        <t>Microwave transceivers</t>
        <t>Optical repeaters</t>
        <t>etc.</t></list>
      </t>
      <t>
    Each network may support different technologies and an E2E network slice is a combination of these networks. As an example:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Network 1 might contain multiple 5G RAN nodes connected to a few Cell Site Gateways (CSG) routers. </t>
        <t>Network 2 might have one or more layer-3 routers and layer-2 switches which may run on top of an optical network.</t>
        <t>Network 3 might have a number of 5G RAN nodes connected to Passive Optical Network (PON) switches.</t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <figure anchor="fig_E2E-NS" title="E2E network slice">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[

        <======================= E2E NS ======================>
        <-OS1-> <-TS1-> <-TS2-> <-OS2->   ...   <-TSn-> <-OSm->
       |------------------------------------------------------|
       |    .--.             .--.                .--.         |
       |   (    )--.        (    )--.           (    )--.     |
       |   .'         '     .'         '        .'        '   |
[EU-x] |  (  Network-1  )  (  Network-2  ) ... (  Network-p ) |[EU-y]
       |   `-----------'    `-----------'       `----------'  |
       |                                                      |
       |                      Operator-z                      |
       |------------------------------------------------------|
Legend:
  E2E NS: End-to-end network slice
  TSn: Transport Slice n
  OSm: Other Slice m
  EU-x: End User-x
  EU-y: End User-y

  ]]></artwork>
      </figure>


      <t>
      When operator-z creates a specific E2E network slice, it may create
      one or more of transport (IETF-network) slices and other slices (application logic or other system functions).
      </t>

      <t>
     An independent E2E logical network (called E2E network slice) is created for a service (e.g. CCTV, autonomous driving, HD map, etc.) with a specific network SLOs,
		e.g. a secure connection with an E2E latency less than 5ms, from End User-x (EU-x) to End User-y (EU-y). EU-x maybe a 5G user equipment such as an infotainment unit in a 
        car, CCTV, or a car for autonomous driving, etc. and
    EU-y in 5G is 5G application server, IMS, etc.
      </t>
      <t>
    In <xref target="fig_E2E-NS"/>,  "E2E NS"  is that logical
    network with requested SLO between EU-x to EU-y and   is
    associated with a customer and a specific service type.
      </t>

	  <!--
      <t>
    As a concrete example, a customer "City of NY" would like to connect all its CCTV cameras for the entire city to one or more locations for viewing or collection. To this end, it requests local carrier - 'operator-z' in NY to create a new E2E network slice with a bandwidth no-less-than 10Mbps from each CCTV coverage area. In this case, a single E2E network slice will be created by the operator-z for the customer "City of NY", service type of CCTV and requested bandwidth connecting all the CCTV camera zones to one or more control-centers for the collection of video data.
      </t>
      <t>
    It may also be possible that more than one customer and/or service types are associated with an E2E network slice.

    For instance, an E2E network slice is associated with not only to service type CCTV
    but another service "Public Safety", i.e. NS ID 10 is used for two services for "City of NY".
      </t>
-->
    </section>



    <section title="Security Considerations">
    <t>
    Not applicable in this memo.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>
    This memo includes no request to IANA.
    </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgment">
    <t>
    The entire TEAS NS design team and everyone participating in those discussion has contributed to this draft. Particularly, 
    Eric Gray, Xufeng Liu, Jie Dong, and Jari Arkko for a thorough review among other contributions.
    </t>
    </section>


 
  </middle>

  <!-- ***** BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
    &I-D.draft-contreras-teas-slice-nbi;
 <!--&I-D.draft-nsdt-teas-ns-framework;
     &I-D.draft-homma-rtgwg-slice-gateway;
    &I-D.draft-ietf-teas-sf-aware-topo-model;
    &I-D.draft-ietf-teas-enhanced-vpn;i-->
    &I-D.draft-ietf-teas-yang-te-topo;
  <!--  &I-D.i2nsf-nsf-monitoring-data-model;
    &I-D.draft-ietf-i2nsf-capability; -->
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2681"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7679"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7680"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3022"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6146"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5921"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4303"?>
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8453"?>    
    <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8345"?>
    
    
      <reference anchor='TS.23.501-3GPP'  target="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp//Specs/archive/23_series/23.501/23501-g20.zip">
        <front>
        <title>3GPP TS 23.501 (V16.2.0): System Architecture for the 5G System (5GS); Stage 2 (Release 16)
        </title>
        <author>
        <organization>
        3rd Generation Partnership Project (3GPP)
        </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="September" year="2019"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

	  <reference anchor="RFC3393" target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc3393">
      <front>
      <title>
      IP Packet Delay Variation Metric for IP Performance Metrics (IPPM)
      </title>
      <author initials="C." surname="Demichelis" fullname="C. Demichelis">
      <organization/>
      </author>
      <author initials="P." surname="Chimento" fullname="P. Chimento">
      <organization/>
      </author>
      <date year="2002" month="November"/>
      </front>
      <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="3393"/>
      <seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.17487/RFC3393"/>
      </reference>
<!--
	  <reference anchor='NFVGST' target="https://www.etsi.org/deliver/etsi_gs/NFV-TST/001_099/008/02.04.01_60/gs_nfv-tst008v020401p.pdf">
        <front>
		<title>
			NFVI Compute and Network Metrics Specification
		</title>
        <author>
        <organization> ETSI </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="February" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
-->

      <reference anchor='TS33.210' target="https://portal.3gpp.org/desktopmodules/Specifications/SpecificationDetails.aspx?specificationId=2279">
        <front>
    <title>
      3G security; Network Domain Security (NDS); IP network layer security (Release 14).
    </title>
        <author>
        <organization> 3GPP </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="December" year="2016"/>
        </front>
      
      </reference>
        <reference anchor='HIPAA' target="https://www.hhs.gov/hipaa/for-professionals/security/index.html">
        <front>
    <title>
      Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act - The Security Rule
    </title>
       <author>
        <organization> HHS </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="February" year="2003"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor='PCI' target="https://www.pcisecuritystandards.org" >
        <front>
    <title>
      PCI DSS 
    </title>
       <author>
        <organization> PCI Security Standards Council </organization>
        </author>
        <date month="May" year="2018"/>
        </front>
      </reference>
      
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
